A Register of the Aleksandr Kallinikovich Svitich Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Kallinikovich Svitich Papers
1921-1965
2008C81
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
These papers provide insight into the life of the Orthodox Church in Poland in the Interwar period. Aleksander K. Svitich, a theologian and member of the faculty of the Vilno Theological Seminary, served on the editorial board of Za svobodu, a Russian émigré newspapers, to which he contributed numerous articles, at times using his pen name Tuberozov. Reflected in these papers are also Svitich's research interests.
Svitich, Aleksandr Kallinikovich
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
The entire collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1890 March 15 Born, Vilno, Russian Empire
19?? Graduated, Theological faculty, Warsaw University
19?? Professor, Vilno Theological Seminary
1921-1932 Editorial board member (pen name Tuberozov), Za svobodu
1930-1933 Editor, V ograde tserkovnoi
1950 Arrived in the U.S.A.
1959 Author, Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' v Pol'she i ee avtokefaliia
1963 August 17 Died, Denver, CO
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers provide insight into the life of the Orthodox Church in Poland in the Interwar period. Aleksander K. Svitich, a theologian and member of the faculty of the Vilno Theological Seminary, served on the editorial board of Za svobodu, a Russian émigré newspapers, to which he contributed numerous articles, at times using his pen name Tuberozov. Reflected in these papers are also Svitich's research interests.
The Subject file contains documents pertaining to the activities of the Orthodox Church in the Unites States. Noteworthy are the correspondence of Archbishop Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), and Archbishop Irinei (Bekish), and documents relating to the Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' zagranitsei.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Subject file, and Printed matter
Related Material
Archbishop Apollinarii (Koshevoi) Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Vladislav Albionovich Maevskii Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Konstantin Nikolaevich Nikolaev Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Nikolai D. Talberg Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Biography
Aleksandr Kallinikovich Svitich was born March 15, 1890, the son of a Russian Orthodox priest, in Vilno, still part of the Russian empire at that time. Following the usual path of children of clergy, he pursued a theological education, graduating from the Theological Faculty of Warsaw University in 1930 and teaching at the Vilno Theological Seminary. Svitich served on the editorial board of Za svobodu, a Russian émigré newspaper, to which he contributed numerous articles, at times using his pen name Tuberozov, and edited V ograde tserkovnoi from 1930 to 1933. As legal adviser to the Orthodox Church in Poland, Svitich actively defended the interests of the Orthodox Church versus the Catholic Church in Poland.
Forced to leave Poland for Serbia in 1937, he settled in Belgrade, where he advised the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia in legal matters. In 1938 Svitich participated in the Second Russian Orthodox All-Diaspora; in 1945, he immigrated to Germany, where he lived in displaced persons camps before arriving in the United States in 1950. Reflecting on his years in Poland and his activities in the Orthodox Church there, he published a historical monograph in 1959 on the Orthodox Church in Poland and the issue of church autocephaly titled Pravoslavnaia Tserkov’ v Pol’she i ee avtokefaliia.
Aleksandr Svitich died on August 17, 1963, in Denver, Colorado.
Eastern Catholic Church.; Orthodox Eastern Church--Poland--History--20th century.; Poland--History.; Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' zagranitsei.
- Biographical file, 1927-1950 and undated. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Address of gratitude, Peretrukhin-Svitich controversy file, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address of gratitude of the Russian Orthodox deanery of the French occupation zone in Germany, 1950 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Peretrukhin-Svitich controversy file, 1927-1934 and undated. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes related materials
- Correspondence, 1926-1949.
  General note
  See also Subject file/Orthodox Eastern Church--Poland--History--20th century/All-Polish council
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Dionisii (Valedinskii), Metropolitan, 1930-1931 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Iakubovich, Viacheslav, Reverend, 1926-1931 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Ioann (Pommer), Archbishop, 1930 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Mikhailovskii, Vladimir, 1926 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Savva (Sovetov), Archbishop, 1949 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Shavel'skii, Georgii, Reverend, 1930 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Za svobodu, 1926-1931 (Folder 1: 9)
- Speeches and writings, 1926-1961 and undated.
  Articles, clippings, letter to the editor, notes, arranged chronologically by title.
  - General
    - Letter to the editor, 1961 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Notes, undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Newspaper articles
      - General, 1953-1959 and undated (Folder 1: 12)
      - Za svobodu
        - 1926 (Folder 1: 13)
        - 1927 (Folder 1: 14)
        - 1928 (Folder 1: 15)
        - 1929-1930 (Folder 1: 16)
  - "Edinaia, sviataia, sobornaia i apostol'skaia tserkov',", undated. (Folder 1: 17)
    Typescript
  - "Nasushchnieishaia nuzhda,", undated. (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Vybornoe nachalo v zhizni pravoslavnoi tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 1: 19)
  - "Znachenie sobornosti v pravoslavnoi tserkvi (v zashchitu sobornosti v zhizni tserkvi),", undated. (Folder 1: 20)
  - "Cherez Golgofu k voskreseniiu," Rossiia, No. 5090, 1953. (Folder 1: 21)
    Printed copy
  - "Tserkov' s pervykh vekov khristiianstva i ee sobornoe ustroenie,", 1953. (Folder 1: 22)
    Typescript, with introductory remarks and notes
- Subject file, 1921-1965 and undated.
  Bylaws, clippings, correspondence, minutes, notebook, pamphlets, reports, research notes, resolutions, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Eastern Catholic Church, clippings, research notes (Folder 1: 23)
  - Orthodox Eastern Church--Poland--History--20th Century (Box 2)
    - General, clippings (Folder 2: 1)
    - All-Polish council. (Folder 2: 2)
      Includes newspaper articles by Svitich and other authors, clippings, related correspondence, notes, and resolutions
    - Persecutions of Orthodox Christians, 1938-1940. (Folder 2: 3)
      Notebook entitled "Gonenie na Pravoslavie v Pol'shie" with pasted clippings
  - Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America
    - Bylaws, The Russian Church of Our Lady of Kazan, Sea Cliff, N.Y., undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), Archbishop, 1935-1937. (Folder 2: 5)
        Includes correspondence with Metropolitan Feofil (Pashkovskii), and Bishop Leontii (Turkevich)
      - Irinei (Bekish), Archbishop, 1965 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Minutes, Ninth All-American council, 1955 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' zagranitsei
    - General
      - Parish bylaws, 1946-1955. (Folder 2: 8)
        Printed copies
      - Skvortsov, Vasilii Mikhailovich. Reports to ecclesiastical councils, 1921-1931 (Folder 2: 9)
    - "Krizis upravleniia Russkoi zarubezhnoi tserkvi,", undated (Folder 2: 10)
    - Tserkovnye zakony kasaiushchiesia Russkoi pravoslavnoi tserkvi zagranitsei, 1947. (Folder 2: 11)
  - Poland--History. Clippings, 1957 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Teodorovich, Terentii, Reverend, 1950-1953 and undated. (Folder 2: 13)
    Clippings and three prints
- Printed matter, 1930-1933 and undated. (Folder 2: 14-15)
  Catalog and clippings